Finding Aid for Henry Howland Crapo Papers 1830-1920
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Miscellaneous (mainly financial)
  - Journals, 3 oversize volumes (Volume 1)
Information on the election of 1862, especially a letter, Nov. 10, 1862, of Henry Crapo to his son William Crapo.
Elections--Michigan--1888.
Letter, Nov. 7, 1888, of H. C. Potter, Jr. to William W. Crapo discussing the results of the election of 1888 in Michigan in considerable detail.
Fairfield (Mich.)
Letters in the 1840's and 1850's of Orrin Baker of Fairfield, Lenawee Co., about Crapo's land dealings in that area but including full and frequent comments on local news, weather, agriculture, etc.
Fenton, William M., 1808-1871.
Letters, March 17 and March 22, 1856, from William Fenton to Crapo chiefly about land matters.
Fentonville (Mich.)
Information about Fentonville in the correspondence for 1856-1857.
Flint and Holly Railroad Company.
Material in the correspondence, 1862-1864, on the building, financing, and operation of the Flint and Holly Railroad, of which Crapo was the chief promoter.
Flint and Pere Marquette Railway Company.
Material on the Flint and Pere Marquette Railroad in the correspondence for 1862 and 1888; also some material in the other papers.
Gilman, Daniel Coit, 1831-1908.
Letter, March 3,1857, of Daniel Coit Gilman to W. W. Crapo, asking for reports of the Mass. farm and reform school and annual prison reports, for a paper he was writing on juvenile crime.
Green, Noah K., 1808-1886.
Copy of a letter, March 23, 1864, from Noah Green about Crapo's candidacy for governor.
Isle Royale Mining Company.
Reports to stockholders, Dec. 1, 1855 and Mar. 19, 1856, of the Isle Royale Mining Company.
Jackson, Lansing and Saginaw Railroad Company.
Letter, July 15, 1867, from. James Turner to H. H. Crapo concerning the Jackson, Lansing, and Saginaw Railroad.
Joy, James Frederick, 1810-1896.
Letter, March 4, 1867, from James F. Joy on Crapo's veto of the railroad bills.
Kalamazoo and Schoolcraft Railroad Company.
Material on the Kalamazoo and Schoolcraft Railroad in the correspondence for Jan. and Feb. 1867.
Kalamazoo County (Mich.)
Material on Kalamazoo County in the correspondence for the 1850's. Most of the letters deal with land.
Kellogg, John R., 1793-1868.
Letters of March 4 and 7, 1867, of John Kellogg on the Crapo veto of railroad legislation.
Land use--Michigan.
Correspondence in the 1840's and 1850's dealing with Crapo's land holdings and purchases in Michigan, Ohio, and Iowa, and giving a vivid picture of activity in land sales during the period.
Leach, DeWitt C., b. 1832.
Letter, June 25, 1868, from D. C. Leach on the possibility of Crapo being a candidate for the Senate that year; also copies of letters, April-May 1864, from C. D. Leach.
Ledyard, Henry, 1812-1880.
Letters of Nov. 6, and Dec. 26, 1855, of Henry Ledyard, concerning land purchases.
Lenawee County (Mich.)
Letters in the 1840's and 1850's of Orrin Baker of Fairfield, Lenawee Co., about Crapo's land dealings in that area including full and frequent comments on local news, weather, agriculture, etc.
Lumbering--Michigan.
Detailed materials on his lumbering interests in the correspondence for 1855-1869, and also material in the other papers.
Macomb County (Mich.)
Letters, especially one of September 18, 1854, discussing the Dutch settlement in Macomb county and other matters.
Marathon (Mich.)
Material on Marathon, especially Crapo's lumberyard there, in the correspondence and other papers.
Marquette & Ontonagon Railroad Company.
Material on the Marquette and Ontonagon Railroad pertaining to the railroad vetoes.
Mears, Charles B., 1814-1895.
Copy of a letter, March 24, 1864, on Crapo's candidacy for governor from Charles Mears.
Mercer, William, b. 1824.
Letters, 1855, from William Mercer of Ionia County, mostly about land matters.
Monroe County (Mich.)
Information about Monroe County, particularly about land sales there, in the correspondence for the 1850's.
Odessa (Mich.)
Letters, 1853-1855, to Crapo from his brother David who settled in Odessa, Michigan as a farmer and wrote fully about conditions there.
Pitcher, Zina, 1797-1872.
Letter, April 12, 1867, of Zina Pitcher, about Crapo's Veto of the Detroit Public Works Bill.
Railroads--Michigan.
Correspondence and other papers dealing with Michigan railroads, among them the Oakland and Ottawa Railroad, described in a letter of Dec. 28, 1854 and Apr. 2, 1855; Lansing and Saginaw Railroad, March 26, 1856; and much material on the Flint and Holly and the Flint and Pere Marquette; also papers and correspondence on Crapo's vetoes of the railroad acts.
Republican Party (Mich.)
Correspondence and other papers dealing with Crapo's term in the State Senate, two terms as Governor on the Republican ticket; also a letter, October 2, 1855, from Crapo to his son discussing the formation of the Republican Party In Massachusetts.
Roads--Michigan.
Letter of Crapo to his brother, dated Feb. 24, 1853, discussing the effect of plank roads on land prices.
Saginaw and Lansing Rail Road Company.
Letter, March 26, 1856, of G. G. Dorr to Crapo about the Lansing and Saginaw Railroad.
Salt industry and trade--Michigan
Material on salt drilling near Flint in the correspondence for 1862 and 1863.
Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874.
Copy of a letter, May 17, 1858, from Crapo to Smith re business dealings in lands; also copy of Gerrit Smith's answer, May 28, 1858; also copy of letter, May 31, 1858, to Smith from Crapo.
Smith, Humphrey Henry Howland Crapo.
Correspondence with Humphrey Smith, son-in-law and business associate of Gov. Crapo, particularly after 1866.
Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866.
Letter, July 5, 1853, from Jared Sparks about the purchase of western lands.
Standish, John H., b. 1816.
Letter, July 1, 1868, of John Standish, urging the Senatorial candidacy of Crapo.
Trowbridge, Rowland E., 1821-1881.
Letter, April 4, 1867, of Rowland Trowbridge on the public reaction to Crapo's veto of railroad legislation.
Turner, James, 1820-1869.
Letter, July 15, 1867, of James Turner on the Jackson, Lansing, and Saginaw Railroad.
United States. Army. Michigan Cavalry Regiment, 3rd (1861-1866)
correspondence, Mar. 1866, about obtaining the release from prison of the 3rd Michigan Cavalry and having them mustered out.
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Correspondence relating to the Civil War's effect on business conditions, the drilling of Flint regiments, and the release from prison and mustering out of the 3rd Michigan Cavalry; also speeches to soldiers and clippings relating to Michigan's war effort.
Warner, William, 1812-1868.
Letter, August 14, 1867, about a constitutional convention.
Williams, Harvey, 1812-1867.
Letters, 1854-1856, of Harvey Williams of Eaton County, dealing principally with land matters.
Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.
Letter, March 22, 1866, from Winchell to H .H. Crapo about a geological survey of the Upper Peninsula.
Wisner, Moses, 1815-1863.
Correspondence, June 1858, with W. S. Driggs about dealings with Wisner.
Withey, Solomon L., 1820-1886.
Letters of S. L. Withey, especially one of June 20, 1868, about the Senatorial election.
Woodman, Jonathan J., b. 1825.
Letter, June 22, 1868, from Jonathan Woodman, on the possibility of Crapo being a candidate for the Senate that year.
Yellowstone National Park.
Letter, April 3, 1878, from P. W. Norris, superintendent of Yellowstone Park, to W. W. Crapo, then congressman from Massachusetts, requesting Crapo's good offices on the park protection bill then before the House appropriations committee